Guide to the Raisa Berg Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Raisa Berg Papers,
1898-2006.
Berg, Raisa, 1913-
44 linear feet (73 archival document boxes; 3 oversize flat boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Bakhmeteff Archive New York, NY. 10027
BA#0531
6761446
The papers comprise correspondence, writings, memoirs, personal documents, research materials, photographs, drawings, printed materials of Raisa L'vovna Berg (1913-2006), prominent geneticist and biologist.
Biographical Note
Raisa L'vovna Berg, prominent geneticist, evolutionary biologist, specialist in population and evolutionary genetics and morphology, historian of science, defender of human rights in the Soviet Union, self educated painter, author of numerous publications and published memoirs, was born on March 27, 1913 in St. Petersburg, in the family of the member of the Russian Academy of Sciences Lev Semenovich Berg.
In 1935 Berg graduated from the Department of Genetics and Experimental Zoology of the Leningrad State University. Her diploma studies were done at the Institute of Genetics, Russian Academy of Sciences, under supervision of the future Nobel Prize winner Hermann Muller. In 1939, Berg defended her dissertation and moved to Moscow and began her doctorate studies at the Severtsov Institute of Evolutionary Morphology of Animals. From 1944 to 1947, Raisa Berg worked as a senior researcher at the Severtsov Institute of Evolutionary Morphology of Animals and part time at the Zoological Institute of Moscow State University. In 1948, she started working as associate professor at the Department of Zoology and Darwinism of the Herzen Leningrad Pedagogical Institute, and in 1949 shifted to the All-Union Research Institute of Lake and River Fish Management. From 1954 to 1957, Raisa Berg worked as an assistant, and from 1957 to 1960, as an associate professor at the Department of Darwinism of Leningrad State University. In 1954, Berg was awarded the academic degree of senior research associate in genetics; in 1957, that of associate professor. In this period, she lectured on evolutionary genetics and genetic bases of evolution and on Darwinism at the Faculty of Biology and Soil Science of Leningrad State University. In 1960 through 1963, she was appointed a senior research associate of the Biological Institute of this University. In 1963, on invitation by the director of the Institute of Cytology and Genetics, she moved to Akademgorodok near Novosibirsk. In this institute, she organized the Laboratory of Population Genetics, which she headed from August of 1963 through June 1968. In 1964, Raisa Berg defended doctoral dissertation at the Komarov Botanical Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences (Leningrad). She was elected a member of the Academic Council of the Institute of Cytology and Genetics. She worked as a lecturer at the Biological Department of the Natural Science Faculty of Novosibirsk State University, giving courses on history of biology and Darwinism (1964-1965) and on population and evolution genetics (1965-1968). In 1968, along with 46 researchers working in institutions of the Siberian Division of the Russian Academy of Sciences, Raisa Berg signed a letter to the Prosecutor General of the Soviet Union and the Supreme Court of the Russian Federation claiming the inadmissibility of conducting closed trials of dissidents. On March 4, 1968, the Academic Council of the Institute of Cytology and Genetics condemned Berg for "political irresponsibility," which manifested in her signing the letter. Shortly after that, in June 1968, Berg was retired from work. She has returned to Leningrad. From 1968 to 1970, Berg heads a group in the Agrophysical Institute of VASKhNIL (All-Union Academy of Agricultural Sciences); in 1968-1974, she was a professor of Leningrad Pedagogical University. In December 1974, Raisa Berg emigrated to the United States, where she worked at University of Wisconsin (Madison) from 1975 through 1981. In 1981, she moved to St. Louis, Missouri, where worked for three years as a visiting professor at the Washington University. During her "American period", Raisa Berg participated in numerous conferences around the world, lectured in Germany and Nehterlands. In 1994, she moved to France.
Raisa Berg died on March 1, 2006, in Paris and was buried in the Pere Lachaise cemetery.
Sources: Zakharov, I.K., Kolosova, L.D., Shumny, V.K. Raisa L’vovna Berg (March 27, 1913–March 1, 2006)
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection consists of Raisa Berg's professional and personal correspondence, her manuscripts, research notes, and photographs. There are also personal documents, biographical materials, extensive collection of reprints and publications on genetics and biology by various authors, art works, and materials related to her human rights activity.
Berg corresponded with many prominent scholars, leading biologists, geneticists, historians, writers, political activists from Russia, USA, Germany, France, Israel including Ivan Shmal'gauzen, Vladimir Efroimson, Vadim Delone, Zhores Medvedev, Naum Korzhavin, Alik Ginzburg, Andrei Sakharov, and many others.
The collection contains Berg's scientific writings, articles and publications on the history of science, her dissertations, memoirs, essays about various people and on popular science, publicistic works, her prose and poetry. Files include published and unpublished works, extensive research notes and data, drafts and fragments.
The collection includes photographs of many prominent scholars, poets and writers, political activists. There are also slides and negatives of R.Berg graphic works and paintings. Among research and reference materials there is an extensive collection of reprints and publications on genetics and biology by various authors, including some rare editions.
There are cross-references provided throughout the finding aid. When the cross-reference refers to another item within the same series, the reference includes the specific name or title and box and folder number (this also applies to the references within same subseries and sub-subseries). If the cross-reference is to an item in another series, the reference includes the series number, series name, folder title, and box and folder numbers (this also applies to references to the items in another subseries and sub-subseries).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1941-2005
Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals, 1941-2005
Subseries I.2: Correspondence with Organizations, 1975-2001
Series II: Works and Writings by R.Berg: Research Data and Notes, 1937-2006
Subseries II.1: Scientific Writings and Works on the History of Science, 1937-2002
Subseries II.2: Memoirs, 1980s-1990s
Subseries II.3: Essays about Various People and on Popular Science; Publicistic Works, 1950s-2006
Subseries II.4: Prose and Poetry, 1940s-1990s
Subseries II.5: Fragments, extracts, notes, and loose pages from various unidentified works, undated
Series III: Human Rights Activity, 1975-1990s
Series IV: Personal Documents and Biographical Materials, 1939-2003
Series V: Photographs, Art Works, and Video-Audio Materials, 1898-2000
Series VI: Research and Reference Materials, 1919-2004
Subseries VI.1: Writings by Others, 1919-2003
Subseries VI.2: Printed Materials, 1937-2004
Subseries VI.3: Various research and reference materials, 1939-2004
Subjects
Alpatov, V. V. (Vladimir Vladimirovich), b. 1898.; Berg, L. S. (Lev Semenovich), 1876-1950.; Binevich, E. M. (Evgenii Mikhaĭlovich).; Bonnėr, Elena, 1923-; Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996.; Chetverikov, S. S. (Sergei Sergeevich), 1880-1959.; Delone, Vadim, 1947-1983.; Ėfroimson, V. P. (Vladimir Pavlovich), 1908-1989.; Ėtkind, E. G. (Efim Grigor'evich), 1918-1999.; Gershenzon, S. M. (Sergei Mikhailovich).; Ginzburg, Aleksandr, 1936-2002.; Ignatov, Pavel Grigor'evich.; Korzhavin, N. (Naum), 1925-; Liubishchev, A.A. (Aleksandr Aleksandrovich), 1890-1972.; Medvedev, Zhores A., 1925-; Meilakh, Mikhail.; Popovskii, Mark Aleksandrovich.; Sakharov, Andrei, 1921-1989.; Shmal'gauzen, I. I. (Ivan Ivanovich), 1884-1963.; Shvarts, Evgenii, 1896-1958.; Smakov, Gennady.; Sosnora, Viktor.; Starovoitova, G. V. (Galina Vasil'evna).; Timofeev-Resovskii, N. V. (Nikolai Vladimirovich), 1900-1981.; Vorontsov, N. N. q(Nikolai Nikolaevich).; Biology--Soviet Union--History.; Dissenters--Soviet Union--Correspondence.; Geneticists--Soviet Union.; Genetics--Soviet Union--History.; Human Rights--Soviet Union.; Refuseniks--Soviet Union.; Art Works.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Memoirs.; Photographs.; Printed Ephemera.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Mme Elisaveth Kirpitchnikov Purchase. 2008
- Series I: Correspondence, 1941-2005
  The series consists of Berg's professional and personal correspondence with various people and organizations and includes letters from many prominent figures. Correspondence includes various related materials, such as manuscripts and clippings. Organized in two subseries.
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals, 1941-2005
    Contains professional and personal letters (many with Raisa Berg's replies) of various individuals including many prominent scholars, writers, poets, and public figures. Arranged alphabetically. Unidentified, family, and outgoing letters, group greetings and postcards are stored at the end of the series. Unidentified correspondence organized chronologically; outgoing letters to identified addressees organized alphabetically and to unidentified addressees in chronological sequence.
    - Adams, Mark, Aspen, Philadelphia1975-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Afonina, Natal'ia, (aka Afonina-Ashkenazi), Doylestown, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aizenzon, Grigorii Aleksandrovich, Denver, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aizenzon, Marina, Denver, Kiev, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Alcibiade, Ada, New York, Rome, Venice, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Aleksandrov, Andrei Samuilovich, Leningrad, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aleksandrov, Daniil, Leningrad, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aleksandrov, Igor' D., Dubna, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Aleksandrov, Vladimir Iakovlevich, Leningrad, 1979-1990 (including clippings from Znanie-Sila with his publication "Trudnye gody sovetskoi biologii: iz zapisok sovremennika") (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Aleksandrova, Margarita V., Dubna, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Aleksandrova, Marianna Leont'evna, Leningrad, 1978 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Alpatov, Vladimir Vladimirovich:
      - To R.L. Berg, Moscow, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - To F.G. Dobzhanskii (aka Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich), 1971-1975 (photocopies) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Altukhov, Iurii Petrovich, Moscow, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Amert, Susan, Iowa City, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Aminov, Amri, Paris, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Anders, Fritz, 1980 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Aoki, Kenichi, Japan, undated, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Apter, Esfira, Rome, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Aronova, Elena A., Moscow, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Arronet, Nikolai I., Leningrad, undated, 1990-2001 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ashkinazi, Ester, Parsippany, NJ, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Astaurov, B.L. to F.G. Dobzhanskii and other people, Moscow, 1969-1974 (photocopies. See related materials in Subseries I.2: Correspondence with Organizations--Magazines--Quarterly Review of Biology Box 24, Folder 14) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Auerbach, C., Edinburgh, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Autrum, H., Munich, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Babkov, Vasilii Vasil'evich: (Box 2, Folder 1 to 7)
      - To Bentley Glass, St.Louis, 1991 (including typescript of his article "Between Science and Poetry: Velimir Khlebnikov's 'Metabiosis'") (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - To Raisa Berg, Moscow, undated, 1988-2003 (Box 2, Folder 2 to 5)
      - To Elizaveta Kirpichnikova, Moscow, 1994-2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - To Stanislav Maletskii, Moscow, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Bailey, Jo Ann, Helsinki, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Baumberg, Simon, Leeds, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Bednar, John J., Madison, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Beliaev, Nikolai, Birmingham, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Beling, Adelaida Maksimovna (aka Belina), Gettingen, 1986-1987 (see also Regel' correspondence in Box 16, Folder 3) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Belkina, Sarra, Philadelphia, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Belkovskii, Andrei, Moscow, undated, 1990-1993 (including typescript of his article) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Bellot, Francoise, Besancon, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Benson, David, Bogota, Fond du Las, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Beregovoi, Vladimir Efimovich, various places, undated, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Berg, Lev. Letter to V.S.Kirpichnikov, 1942 see Kirpichnikov
    - Berg, John, van de, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Berthoff, Rachel, New York, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Bileva, Dzhemma Serafimovna, Moscow, 1991 1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Binevich, Evgenii Mikhailovich, Leningrad, undated, 1975-2004 (Box 2, Folder 14 to 19)
    - Bird, Margaret G., Huntington, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Birger, Aleksandr, New York, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Birshtein, Vadim, New York, undated, 1996-2003 (including photocopy of his article) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Blenney, Laurence, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bodin, Mark, Amsterdam, Paris, undated, 1998 2004 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Bogdanov Family, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bolas, Gerald D., St.Louis, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bonner, Elena, Newton, 1986 (including undated greeting card from her children to R.Berg) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Borodkin, Fred, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Borodkina, Tamara, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Brink, J. (Mrs. R.Alexander Brink), Madison, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Brink, Janny Margaretha, van, Bilthoven, Utrecht, 1979-1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Brozgul, Leonard, Long Island City, undated, 1985-1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Brumberg, Abraham, Washington, D.C., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Burleigh, Jessica, Madison, undated, 1979-1989 (Box 3, Folder 9 to 10)
    - Burnek, Barrie, Sheffield, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Buzhevskaia, Tamara Ivanovna, Kiev, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Buzzati-Traverso, Adriano, Rome, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Carson, Hampton L., Honolulu, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Chacon, Lutecia, (aka Gonzales-Quintanilla), various places, 1982-1999 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Chell, Jeffrey, Madison, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Cherepenko, Elena Iosifovna, Kiev, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Chin, Audrey, Brantford, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Chudnovskii, A., Cleveland, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Churchill, Federick B., Bloomington, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Cohen, Barry Mendel, various places, 1982-1991 (including photocopies of his publications) (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Cohen, Larry W., Industry, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Crow, James F., Madison, 1975-1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Cutchins, Ernest C., Washington D.C., 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Daiter, Arkadii, New York, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Daniels, Robert V., Burlington, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - David, Jean, Lyon, 1976 1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Dean, Susan and Tony, St.Louis, undated, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Delbruck, Max, Pasadena, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Delone, Irina, Paris, undated, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Delone, Vadim, Paris, 1978 (including typescript of his poetry) (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Demech-Marcaillou, Elena, Fontainebleau, 1985-2004 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Demidov, Sergei, Moscow, Djursholm, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Dintin, Maryam Aronovna, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Doktorova, Larisa, Bruxelles, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Drayna, Dennis T., 1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Druian, Nonna Arkad'evna, Moscow, undated, 1984-1995 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Dubois, Alain, Paris, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Dudakova, Inna, Jerusalem, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Dudin, Anna and Georgii, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Dunn, Stephen P., Berkeley, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Dye, Daniel M., St.Louis, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Ebert, James D., Washington, D.C., 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Edelman, Bacia, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Efroimson, Vladimir Pavlovich, various places, undated, 1957-1988 (see also Torrieri):
      - Undated (Box 4, Folder 5 to 7)
      - 1957 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - 1958 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - 1959 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - 1960-1970s (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - 1985 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - 1986 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Photocopies of selected letters (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - About him (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Elens, Antoine, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Elkin, Zinaida Borisovna, Edison, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Epel'man, Grigorii and Galina, Norfolk, undated, 1976-1985 (Box 5, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Esenin-Vol'pin, Aleksandr, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Etkind, Efim Grigor'evich, France, undated, 1974-1998 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Evgeniev, Mikhail, Baltimore, 1990 1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Faizi, Madras, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Fedicheva, Kaleria, Glen Cove, 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Felton, Sanoy, Charlottesville, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Fet, Abram Il'ich, Novosibirsk, 1975-2003 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Fet, Aleksandr, Branford, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Fet, Evgeniia, Portland, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Fet, Iakov Il'ich, Novosibirsk, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Fet, Viktor, Huntington, New Orleans, 1994-1999 (including photocopy of his article) (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Feyerabend, Paul, London, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Flioss (aka Floss), V.E., Novosibirsk, 1978-1979 (see his notes written on Nikoro's letters in Nikoro's correspondence) (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Ford, Charles, St. Louis, 1988-1990 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Forest, Herman S., Geneseo, 1980-1994 (including a typescript of his essay "From a window on Nevsky prospect") (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - France, Michel, 1978-1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Gateff, Elizabeth, Germany, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Gehring, Walter J., Schweiz, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Gerasimova, Tatiana, 1990 undated (see also Evgeniev) (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Gershenzon, Sergei Mikhailovich, Kiev, 1978-1992 (including publications about him) (Box 5, Folder 16 to 17)
    - Gimel'farb, Aleksandr, Rome, undated, 1976-1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Ginzburg, Aleksandr (Alik)
      - To Julia Juris, Paris, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - To Charles Ronsac, Paris, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Ginzburg, E.Kh., Novosibirsk, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Ginzburg, Lev R., various places, 1976-1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Gittel'zon, Il'ia, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Glass, Bentley: see his letters of 1979-1980 in Subseries I.2: Correspondence with Organizations--Quarterly Review of Biology (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - Glenney, Robert, Grand Forks, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Gliner, Erast, St. Louis, 1984-1994 (see also his works in Series VI: Research and Reference Materials-- Subseries VI.1: Writings by Others--Gliner--Box 63, Folder 6) (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Godlevskaia, Marina, Helsinki, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Golberg, I.S., Madison, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Goldenberg, Liudmila, Newark, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Golenpolsky, T., (Golenpol'skii), Moscow, 1975 1979 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Golodets, E.S., Tel-Aviv, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Golovanov, L., undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Golubovskii, Mikhail Davidovich, Novosibirsk, 1973-2004 (see also his note written on Nikoro's letter of 1978 in Nikoro' correspondence) (Box 6, Folder 8 to 11)
    - Gonzales-Quintanilla, Lutecia: see Chacon
    - Gorbunova, Viktoriia N., Leningrad, 1991 undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Gorbushin, Nikolai Grigor'evich, 1993 (about Nikolai Vladimirovich Timofeev-Resovskii) (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Gouindaraju, D.R., Rutgers, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Grafodatskie, Aleksandr and Viktoriia, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Graham, Loren, Cambridge, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Graham, Madge Yang, St.Lous, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Graugers, Charles and Cheryl (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Green, Mel, Davis, 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Grem, Richard, Terryville, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Griunval'd, Lidiia and Leonid, Utica, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Grosman, Alik (aka Abram Grossman), Iowa City, Jerusalem, 1975-1978 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Grosman, Evgenii, Carol Stream, Chicago, 1984-1988 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Gudava, Tengiz, Brighton, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Gurvich, Vladimir, New York, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Gusev, Vladimir A., Leningrad, undated, 1975-1989 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Halvorson, H., Milwaukee, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Harding, Susan: see Dean (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Harvye, Jean, Madison, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Haymer, Beatrez and David, Irvine, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Hoffman, Robert S., Washington D.C., 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Hollander, Alexander, Washington, D.C., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Holiday, Robin, London, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Holmes, Steve and Ann, Arlington, Marshall, undated, 1981-2002 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Holtmeier, Klaus, Germany, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Honeycutt, Ann, St.Louis, 1983-1985 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Hook, Ernest B., Albany, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Howell, Yvonne, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Ianovich, L.S., Novosibirsk, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Iasinovskaia, Flora Pavlovna, Moscow, 1977-1994 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Il'inskaia, Kristi, Iowa City, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Ilmin, Howard, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Iltis, Wilfred G., San Jose, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Ionin, Nata, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Ivanov, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Ivanov, D., France, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Ivanov, Iu. N., Novosibirsk, 1975-1981 (Box 7, Folder 8 to 9)
    - Ivanov, Vladimir, various places, 1977-1998 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Ivanov, Vladimir I., Moscow, 1987-1992 (including his writings) (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Iziumova: see Keshman
    - Jameson, David, Houston, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Jensen, Ken, Gambier, 1980-1982 (including his essay "Red star: Bogdanov builds a utopia") (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Joern, Ed, St.Louis, 1990 undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Kagan, Viktor Kusielevich, Jerusalem, 1976-1990 (Box 8, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Kaganov, Grigorii, St.Petersburg, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Kaidanov, Leonid Zinov'evich, Leningrad, 1981-1995 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Kanaev, I.I., Leningrad, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Kaplan, Bill, Duarte, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Karpov, Sviatoslav, Rockville, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Karpova, Tat'iana S., St. Louis, 1993-2003 (Box 8, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Karpovskaia, Elena, Novosibirsk, 1980-2000 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Kastenmeier, Bob, Madison, Washington, DC, 1977 1979 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Kay, Regina, Cambridge, New York, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Kendall, Annabel, Madison, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Keshman, Elena, Jerusalem, Moscow, 1990-2001 (her essay about Vladimir Efroimson see in Efroimson's correspondence: Box 4, Folder 17) (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Khalif, Lev, New York, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Kharash: see Krupitskaia
    - Khoury, Muin J., Atlanta, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Kidwell, Margaret, Providence, 1977-1982 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Kinball, Eona, Beverly, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Kirina, Liudmila, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Kirk, Irina, Lahaina, St. Louis, 1987-1990 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Kirpichnikov, Valentin Sergeevich: